const quizQuestions = [

  {

      question: "Who is the father of C language?",

      options: ["Steve Jobs","James Gosling","Dennis Ritchi","Rasmus Lerdorf"],

      correctAnswer: "Dennis Ritchi"

  },

  {

    question: "Which type of Programming does Python support?",

    options: ["object-oriented","structured","functiona","all of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "all of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "Is Python case sensitive when dealing with identifiers?",

    options: ["No","Yes","machine dependent","none of the above"],

    correctAnswer: "Yes"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is the correct extension of the Python file?",

    options: [".python",".pl",".py",".p"],

    correctAnswer: ".py"

  },

  {

    question: "All keywords in Python are in _________",

    options: ["Capitalized","lower case","UPPER CASE","None of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "None of the mentioned"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is used to define a block of code in Python language?",

    options: ["Indentation","Key","Brackets","All of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "Indentation"

  },


  {

    question: "Which keyword is used for function in Python language?",

    options: ["function","def","fun","define"],

    correctAnswer: "def"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following character is used to give single-line comments in Python?",

    options: ["//","#","!","/*"],

    correctAnswer: "#"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following functions can help us to find the version of python that we are currently working on?",

    options: ["sys.version(1)","sys.version(0)","sys.version()","sys.version"],

    correctAnswer: "sys.version"

  },


  {

    question: "Python supports the creation of anonymous functions at runtime, using a construct called __________",

    options: ["pi","anonymous","lambda","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "lambda"

  },


  {

    question: "What does pip stand for python?",

    options: ["Pip Installs Python","Pip Installs Packages","Preferred Installer Program","All of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "Preferred Installer Program"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is the truncation division operator in Python?",

    options: ["|","//","/","%"],

    correctAnswer: "//"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions is a built-in function in python?",

    options: ["factorial()","print()","seed()","sqrt()"],

    correctAnswer: "print()"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is not a core data type in Python programming?",

    options: ["Tuples","Lists","Class","Dictionary"],

    correctAnswer: "Class"

  },


  {

    question: "To add a new element to a list we use which Python command?",

    options: ["list1.addEnd(5)","list1.addLast(5)","list1.append(5)","list1.add(5)"],

    correctAnswer: "list1.append(5)"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the maximum possible length of an identifier in Python?",

    options: ["79 characters","31 characters","63 characters","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "none of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "What are the two main types of functions in Python?",

    options: ["System function","Custom function","Built-in function & User defined function","User function"],

    correctAnswer: "Built-in function & User defined function"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is a Python tuple?",

    options: ["{1, 2, 3}","{}","[1, 2, 3]","(1, 2, 3)"],

    correctAnswer: "(1, 2, 3)"

  },


  {

    question: "What is output of print(math.pow(3, 2))?",

    options: ["9.0","None","9","None of the above"],

    correctAnswer: "9.0"

  },


  {

    question: "Is Python case sensitive when dealing with identifiers?",

    options: ["yes","no","machine dependent","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "yes"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the maximum possible length of an identifier?",

    options: ["31 characters","63 characters","79 characters","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "none of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is invalid?",

    options: ["_a = 1","__a = 1","__str__ = 1","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "none of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is an invalid variable?",

    options: ["my_string_1","1st_string","foo","_"],

    correctAnswer: "1st_string"

  },



  {

    question: "Which of the following is not a keyword?",

    options: ["eval","assert","nonlocal","pass"],

    correctAnswer: "eval"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is an invalid statement?",

    options: ["abc = 1,000,000","a b c = 1000 2000 3000","a,b,c = 1000, 2000, 3000","a_b_c = 1,000,000"],

    correctAnswer: "a b c = 1000 2000 3000"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following cannot be a variable?",

    options: ["__init__","in","it","on"],

    correctAnswer: "in"

  },


  {

    question: "Which is the correct operator for power(xy)?",

    options: ["x^y","x**y","x^^y","None of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "x**y"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the answer to this expression, 22 % 3 is?",

    options: ["7","1","0","5"],

    correctAnswer: "1"

  },


  {

    question: "Operators with the same precedence are evaluated in which manner?",

    options: ["Left to Right","Right to Left","Can't say","None of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "Left to Right"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the output of this expression, 3*1**3?",

    options: ["27","9","3","1"],

    correctAnswer: "3"

  },

  {

    question: "Which one of the following has the highest precedence in the expression?",

    options: ["Exponential","Addition","Multiplication","Parentheses"],

    correctAnswer: "Parentheses"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of these in not a core data type?",

    options: ["Lists","Dictionary","Tuples","Class"],

    correctAnswer: "Class"

  },

  {

    question: "Given a function that does not return any value, What value is thrown by default when executed in shell.",

    options: ["int","bool","void","None"],

    correctAnswer: "None"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following will run without errors?",

    options: [" round(45.8)","round(6352.898,2,5)","round()","round(7463.123,2,1)"],

    correctAnswer: "round(45.8)"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the return type of function id?",

    options: ["int","float","bool","dict"],

    correctAnswer: "int"

  },


  {

    question: "In order to store values in terms of key and value we use what core data type.",

    options: ["list","tuple","Class","dictionary"],

    correctAnswer: "dictionary"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the output of print 0.1 + 0.2 == 0.3?",

    options: ["True","false","machine dependent","Error"],

    correctAnswer: "False"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is not a complex number?",

    options: ["k = 2 + 3j","k = complex(2, 3)","k = 2 + 3l","k = 2 + 3J"],

    correctAnswer: "k = 2 + 3l"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the type of inf?",

    options: ["Boolean","Integer","Float","Complex"],

    correctAnswer: "Float"

  },

  {

    question: "What does ~4 evaluate to?",

    options: ["-5","-4","-3","+3"],

    correctAnswer: "-5"

  },

  {

    question: "What does ~~~~~~5 evaluate to?",

    options: ["+5","-11","+11","-5"],

    correctAnswer: "+5"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following is incorrect?",

    options: [" x = 30963"," x = 0x4f5","x = 19023","x = 03964"],

    correctAnswer: "x = 03964"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the result of cmp(3, 1)?",

    options: ["1","0","True","False"],

    correctAnswer: "1"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the result of round(0.5) – round(-0.5)?",

    options: ["1.0","2.0","0.0","value depends on python version"],

    correctAnswer: "value depends on python version"

  },


  {

    question: "What does 3 ^ 4 evaluate to?",

    options: ["81","12","0.75","7"],

    correctAnswer: "7"

  },

  {

    question: "What arithmetic operators cannot be used with strings?",

    options: ["+","*","-","all of the above"],

    correctAnswer: "-"

  },

  {

    question: "Given a string example=”hello” what is the output of example.count('l')?",

    options: ["2","1","none","0"],

    correctAnswer: "2"

  },

  {

    question: "To concatenate two strings to a third what statements are applicable?",

    options: ["s3 = s1 . s2","s3 = s1.add(s2)","s3 = s1.__add__(s2)","s3 = s1 * s2"],

    correctAnswer: "s3 = s1.__add__(s2)"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following commands will create a list?",

    options: ["list1 = list()","list1 = []","list1 = list([1, 2, 3])","all of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "all of the mentioned"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the output when we execute list(“hello”)?",

    options: ["[‘h’, ‘e’, ‘l’, ‘l’, ‘o’]","[‘hello’]"," [‘llo’]","[‘olleh’]"],

    correctAnswer: "[‘h’, ‘e’, ‘l’, ‘l’, ‘o’]"

  },

  {

    question: "Suppose listExample is [‘h’,’e’,’l’,’l’,’o’], what is len(listExample)?",

    options: ["5","4","None","Error"],

    correctAnswer: "5"

  },

  {

    question: "Suppose list1 is [2445,133,12454,123], what is max(list1)?",

    options: ["2445","133","12454","123"],

    correctAnswer: "12454"

  },

  {

    question: " Suppose list1 is [3, 5, 25, 1, 3], what is min(list1)?",

    options: ["3","1","5","25"],

    correctAnswer: "1"

  },


  {

    question: "Suppose list1 is [1, 5, 9], what is sum(list1)?",

    options: ["1","9","15","error"],

    correctAnswer: "15"

  },

  {

    question: "To shuffle the list(say list1) what function do we use?",

    options: ["list1.shuffle()"," shuffle(list1)","random.shuffle(list1)","random.shuffleList(list1)"],

    correctAnswer: "random.shuffle(list1)"

  },

  {

    question: "Suppose list1 is [4, 2, 2, 4, 5, 2, 1, 0], Which of the following is correct syntax for slicing operation?",

    options: ["print(list1[2:])","print(list1[:2])","print(list1[:-2])","all of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "all of the mentioned"

  },

  {

    question: "Suppose list1 is [2, 33, 222, 14, 25], What is list1[-1]?",

    options: ["error","None","25","2"],

    correctAnswer: "25"

  },


  {

    question: "Suppose list1 is [2, 33, 222, 14, 25], What is list1[:-1]?",

    options: ["[2, 33, 222, 14]","Error","25"," [25, 14, 222, 33, 2]"],

    correctAnswer: "[2, 33, 222, 14]"

  },

  {

    question: " Which of the following is a Python tuple?",

    options: [" [1, 2, 3]","(1, 2, 3)","{1, 2, 3}"," {}"],

    correctAnswer: "(1, 2, 3)"

  },

  {

    question: "Suppose t = (1, 2, 4, 3), which of the following is incorrect?",

    options: [" print(t[3])","t[3] = 45","print(max(t))","print(len(t))"],

    correctAnswer: "t[3] = 45"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the data type of (1)?",

    options: ["Tuple","Integer","List","Both tuple and integer"],

    correctAnswer: "Integer"

  },


  {

    question: "If a=(1,2,3,4), a[1:-1] is _________",

    options: ["Error, tuple slicing doesn’t exist","[2,3]","(2,3,4)","(2,3)"],

    correctAnswer: "(2,3)"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is not the correct syntax for creating a set?",

    options: ["set([[1,2],[3,4]])","set([1,2,2,3,4])","set((1,2,3,4))","{1,2,3,4}"],

    correctAnswer: "set([[1,2],[3,4]])"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following statements is used to create an empty set?",

    options: ["{}","set()","[]","()"],

    correctAnswer: "set()"

  },

  {

    question: "If a={5,6,7,8}, which of the following statements is false?",

    options: ["print(len(a))","print(min(a))","a.remove(5)","a[2]=45"],

    correctAnswer: "a[2]=45"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following lines of code will result in an error?",

    options: ["s={abs}","s={4, ‘abc’, (1,2)}","s={2, 2.2, 3, ‘xyz’}","s={san}"],

    correctAnswer: "s={san}"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions cannot be used on heterogeneous sets?",

    options: ["pop","remove","update","sum"],

    correctAnswer: "sum"

  },


  {

    question: "The ____________ function removes the first element of a set and the last element of a list.",

    options: ["remove","pop","discard","dispose"],

    correctAnswer: "dispose"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following statements create a dictionary?",

    options: ["d = {}","d = {“john”:40, “peter”:45}","d = {40:”john”, 45:”peter”}","All of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "All of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "Suppose d = {“john”:40, “peter”:45}, to delete the entry for “john” what command do we use?",

    options: ["d.delete(“john”:40)","d.delete(“john”)","del d[“john”]","del d(“john”:40)"],

    correctAnswer: "del d[“john”]"

  },


  {

    question: "Suppose d = {“john”:40, “peter”:45}. To obtain the number of entries in dictionary which command do we use?",

    options: ["d.size()","len(d)"," size(d)","d.len()"],

    correctAnswer: "len(d)"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is not a declaration of the dictionary?",

    options: ["{1: ‘A’, 2: ‘B’}","dict([[1,”A”],[2,”B”]])"," {1,”A”,2”B”}","{}"],

    correctAnswer: " {1,”A”,2”B”}"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions is a built-in function in python?",

    options: ["seed()"," sqrt()","factorial()"," print()"],

    correctAnswer: " print()"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the output of the function complex()?",

    options: ["0j","0+0j","0","Error"],

    correctAnswer: "0j"

  },



  {

    question: "The function divmod(a,b), where both ‘a’ and ‘b’ are integers is evaluated as:",

    options: [" (a%b, a//b)","(a//b, a%b)","(a//b, a*b)","(a/b, a%b)"],

    correctAnswer: "(a//b, a%b)"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following functions does not necessarily accept only iterables as arguments?",

    options: ["enumerate()","all()","chr()","max()"],

    correctAnswer: "chr()"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions accepts only integers as arguments?",

    options: ["ord()","min()","chr()","any()"],

    correctAnswer: "chr()"

  },


  {

    question: "What is the type of each element in sys.argv?",

    options: ["set","list","tuple","string"],

    correctAnswer: "string"

  },

  {

    question: "How many keyword arguments can be passed to a function in a single function call?",

    options: ["zero","one","zero or more","one or more"],

    correctAnswer: "zero or more"

  },


  {

    question: "Which module in the python standard library parses options received from the command line?",

    options: ["getopt","os","getarg","main"],

    correctAnswer: "getopt"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the type of sys.argv?",

    options: ["set","list","tuple","string"],

    correctAnswer: "list"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the value stored in sys.argv[0]?",

    options: ["null","you cannot access it","the program's name","he first argument"],

    correctAnswer: "the program's name"

  },

  {

    question: "Where are the arguments received from the command line stored?",

    options: ["sys.argv","os.argv","argv","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "sys.argv"

  },

  {

    question: " Which of the following data structures is returned by the functions globals() and locals()?",

    options: ["set","list","tuple","dictionary"],

    correctAnswer: "dictionary"

  },


  {

    question: "Program code making use of a given module is called a ______ of the module.",

    options: ["Client","Docstring","Interface","Modularity"],

    correctAnswer: "Client"

  },

  {

    question: " ______ is a string literal denoted by triple quotes for providing the specifications of certain program elements.",

    options: ["Client","Docstring","Interface","Modularity"],

    correctAnswer: "Docstring"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following is not a valid namespace?",

    options: ["Global namespace","Public namespace","Built-in namespace","Local namespace"],

    correctAnswer: "Public namespace"

  },


  {

    question: "What is returned by math.ceil(3.4)?",

    options: ["3","4","4.0","3.0"],

    correctAnswer: "4"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the value returned by math.floor(3.4)?",

    options: ["3","4","4.0","3.0"],

    correctAnswer: "3"

  },

  {

    question: "What will be the output of print(math.copysign(3, -1))?",

    options: ["1","1.0","-3","-3.0"],

    correctAnswer: "-3.0"

  },

  {

    question: "What is displayed on executing print(math.fabs(-3.4))?",

    options: ["-3.4","3.4","3","-3"],

    correctAnswer: "3.4"

  },

  {

    question: "Is the output of the function abs() the same as that of the function math.fabs()?",

    options: ["sometimes","always","never","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "sometimes"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the value returned by math.fact(6)?",

    options: ["720","6"," [1, 2, 3, 6]","error"],

    correctAnswer: "error"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the value of x if x = math.factorial(0)?",

    options: ["0","1","error","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "1"

  },


  {

    question: "What is math.factorial(4.0)?",

    options: ["24","1","error","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "24"

  },


  {

    question: "What will be the output of print(math.factorial(4.5))?",

    options: ["24","120","error","24.0"],

    correctAnswer: "error"

  },

  {

    question: "What is math.floor(0o10)?",

    options: ["8","10","0","9"],

    correctAnswer: "8"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the result of math.fsum([.1 for i in range(20)])?",

    options: ["2.0","20","2","2.0000000000000004"],

    correctAnswer: "2.0"

  },

  {

    question: "What is the result of sum([.1 for i in range(20)])?",

    options: ["2.0","20","2","2.0000000000000004"],

    correctAnswer: "2.0000000000000004"

  },

  {

    question: "What is returned by math.isfinite(float('inf'))?",

    options: ["True","False","None","error"],

    correctAnswer: "False"

  },

  {

    question: "What is returned by math.isfinite(float('nan'))?",

    options: ["True","False","None","error"],

    correctAnswer: "False"

  },

  {

    question: "What is x if x = math.isfinite(float('0.0'))?",

    options: ["True","False","None","error"],

    correctAnswer: "True"

  },


  
  {

    question: "What is the value of x if x = math.ldexp(0.5, 1)?",

    options: ["1","2.0","0.5","none of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "none of the mentioned"

  },


  {

    question: "What is returned by math.modf(1.0)?",

    options: ["(0.0, 1.0)","(1.0, 0.0)","(0.5, 1)","(0.5, 1.0)"],

    correctAnswer: "(0.0, 1.0)"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions helps us to randomize the items of a list?",

    options: ["seed","randomise","shuffle","uniform"],

    correctAnswer: "shuffle"

  },


  {

    question: "Both the functions randint and uniform accept ____________ parameters.",

    options: ["0","1","3","2"],

    correctAnswer: "2"

  },



  {

    question: "What the does random.seed(3) return?",

    options: ["True","None","3","1"],

    correctAnswer: "None"

  },

  {

    question: "Which type of elements are accepted by random.shuffle()?",

    options: ["strings","lists","tuples","integers"],

    correctAnswer: "lists"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following functions is not defined under the sys module?",

    options: ["sys.platform","sys.path","sys.readline","sys.argv"],

    correctAnswer: "sys.readline"

  },


  {

    question: "The output of the function len(sys.argv) is ____________",

    options: ["error","1","0","Junk value"],

    correctAnswer: "1"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following returns a string that represents the present working directory?",

    options: ["os.getcwd()","os.cwd()","os.getpwd()","os.pwd()"],

    correctAnswer: "os.getcwd()"

  },


  {

    question: "Which of the following can be used to create a directory?",

    options: ["os.mkdir()","os.creat_dir()","os.create_dir()","os.make_dir()"],

    correctAnswer: "os.mkdir()"

  },

  {

    question: "In which direction is the turtle pointed by default?",

    options: ["North","South","East","West"],

    correctAnswer: "East"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following functions can accept more than one positional argument?",

    options: ["pickle.dumps","pickle.loads","pickle.dump","pickle.load"],

    correctAnswer: "pickle.dumps"

  },

  {

    question: "The pickle module defines ______ exceptions and exports _______ classes.",

    options: ["2, 3","3, 4","3, 2","4, 3"],

    correctAnswer: "4, 3",

  }

];



// Variables to track quiz state

let currentQuestionIndex = 0;

let score = 0;

let timeLeft = 900; // 15 minutes in seconds

let timerInterval;

let selectedQuestions = []; // Array to hold the selected questions



// Function to start the quiz

function startQuiz() {

  // Shuffle and select 20 random questions

  selectedQuestions = shuffleArray(quizQuestions).slice(0, 20);



  // Hide the start button and display the first question

  document.getElementById("start-button").style.display = "none";

  displayQuestion();

  startTimer();

}



// Function to shuffle an array (Fisher-Yates shuffle)

function shuffleArray(array) {

  for (let i = array.length - 1; i > 0; i--) {

    const j = Math.floor(Math.random() * (i + 1));

    [array[i], array[j]] = [array[j], array[i]];

  }

  return array;

}



// Function to display a question and its options

function displayQuestion() {

  const currentQuestion = selectedQuestions[currentQuestionIndex];

  const questionText = document.getElementById("question-text");

  const answerButtons = document.getElementById("answer-buttons");



  // Clear previous question and answer options

  questionText.innerHTML = "";

  answerButtons.innerHTML = "";



  // Display the current question

  questionText.innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;



  // Create answer buttons for each option

  currentQuestion.options.forEach(option => {

    const button = document.createElement("button");

    button.innerText = option;

    button.classList.add("answer-button");

    answerButtons.appendChild(button);



    // Add click event listener to check the answer

    button.addEventListener("click", function() {

      checkAnswer(option);

    });

  });

}



// Function to check the selected answer

function checkAnswer(selectedOption) {

  const currentQuestion = selectedQuestions[currentQuestionIndex];



  // Check if the selected answer is correct

  if (selectedOption === currentQuestion.correctAnswer) {

    score++;

  }



  // Move to the next question or end the quiz if all questions are answered

  currentQuestionIndex++;



  if (currentQuestionIndex < selectedQuestions.length) {

    displayQuestion();

  } else {

    endQuiz();

  }

}



// function to start the timer

function startTimer() {

  timerInterval = setInterval(function() {

    timeLeft--;



    // Calculate minutes and seconds

    const minutes = Math.floor(timeLeft / 60);

    const seconds = timeLeft % 60;



    // Update the timer text

    document.getElementById("minutes").textContent = minutes;

    document.getElementById("seconds").textContent = seconds < 10 ? "0" + seconds : seconds;



    // End the quiz if time runs out

    if (timeLeft <= 0) {

      endQuiz();

    }

  }, 1000);

}



// Function to end the quiz

function endQuiz() {

  // Stop the timer

  clearInterval(timerInterval);



  // Calculate the score percentage

  const wrongAns = selectedQuestions.length - score;



  // Display the final score

  const questionContainer = document.getElementById("question-container");

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");



  let message = `

    <h2>Quiz Completed!</h2>

    <p id="question-text">Your Score       : ${score} out of ${selectedQuestions.length}</p>

    <p id="question-text">Correct Answers  : ${score}</p>

  `;



  // Check score and show modal if score is less than 5

  if (score < 5) {

    message += `<p id="question-text">Better luck next time!</p>`;

  } else {

    message += `<p id="question-text">Congratulations!</p>`;

  }



  resultsWindow.innerHTML = message;

  resultsWindow.classList.remove("hidden");

}



// Function to close the results modal

function closeResultsModal() {

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");

  resultsWindow.classList.add("hidden");

}



// Add event listener to start the quiz when the start button is clicked

document.getElementById("start-button").addEventListener("click", startQuiz);



// Event listener to close modal when clicking outside

window.addEventListener("click", function(event) {

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");

  if (event.target === resultsWindow) {

    closeResultsModal();

  }

});